we move now to memory virtualization so
let's look a bit more in detail at what happens
when we want to virtualize the memory now
we discussed virtual memory and paging
so you know that the operating system let's
forget about virtualization for a moment
you know that when we have virtual memory
the operating system collaborating with the
hardware it's sort of lying to the processes
thanks to the fact that it completely
decouples the logical view from the physical
view and it not only lets each process believe
it has a sequential set of addresses from zero
to something
but the important thing here is that it actually
makes the processes believe that the memory
they have access to it's actually larger than
the physical memory you really have
in your computer because you are not really
loading all the processes in their entirety
and even if you don't have free frames to
load new parts of a
process you can still reclaim frames either from the
same process or another process as we
discussed so you separate the physical
memory from the logical representation
of it what the process thinks is happening
in the memory
now you want to keep using virtual memory
also if you run an hypervisor because it's
very convenient and efficient it provides
a lot of benefits it's a technique that is
efficient that provides benefits to handle of
the memory
now you probably can agree with me that nonetheless
you cannot really play this game if you have
multiple operating systems at the same time
or at least you cannot play it without extra
care because you need to make each operating
system believe it has access to the memory
while it does not necessarily has it the real mapping
it thinks it has in the physical one so basically
it's like playing the game of virtual memory
but now not between the physical memory and
the processes but now between the physical
memory and the guest operating systems which
in turn will play the same game between their
operating systems their
guest operating system and their processes
so what I'm trying to say is that if you
run two virtual machines and these ones use
virtual memory and they are trying to run
two processes like this each one will have
its page table and each one is allowed to
use the page table to make the process
believe the pages are in memory even if in
fact only some of them might be in the physical
memory and the mapping could be arbitrary
depending on how you are filling
the page table but you cannot do something
like the one
that is shown in this figure because
you cannot make the two processes from two
different operating systems believe that their
page zero is actually in frame one where frame
one is the real frame one in the real hardware
because then of course you are using the same
frame for two different operating systems two
different processes and that is not going
to work so what you do is probably you can
imagine what is going to happen is that you
add an extra layer in between so that the
hypervisor manages the operating system's view
of the memory
and then the operating system manages its
own view of the memory when it comes to interacting
with the processes and what you do is
that you basically introduce a new page
table and this is called the shadow page table
that is maintained by the hypervisor
and is used to translate what each virtual
machine guest operating system sees as a frame
in to the actually real physical frame it
is nonetheless challenging to do this the
challenges are similar in spirit to the ones
you have when you define virtual memory but now
again you have an extra layer you have two layers
at the same
time that you need to take care of you need
to keep the page table at the operating system
at the guest operating system and the shadow
page table at the hypervisor synchronized
they need to be the same because if the
hypervisor thinks something and the guest operating
system thinks something else of course that
will eventually end up
in problems because the guest operating
system will try to access memory that does
not really belong does not necessarily belong to that
process or even to that entire guest operating
system the problem is how do you keep them
in sync?
because the guest operating system can keep
updating its own page tables by just writing
to memory and the instruction it's using
are not necessarily privileged or sensitive
so they don't necessarily trap the hypervisor
so how do you deal with this?
you can go two ways here you can be proactive
so when you see that the operating system
is starting to create page tables (that is done
with a privileged instruction) the hypervisor
can keep track of where in which part of the
memory that is given to that operating system
the operating system is going to maintain
the
page table mark those has read only (read only from
the perspective of the hypervisor of course)
so that whenever the operating system tries
to modify a page table you will
have as a reaction an interrupt that will wake
up the hypervisor and the hypervisor knows
that at that point there is a change being
made in the table and it can
accordingly update the shadow page table
the other alternative is to be lazy and let
the operating system do the guest operating
system do whatever it wants because we know
that at the end of the day as soon as the
operating system actually tries to access
a frame
that does not contain the page it wants then
there will be an interrupt so the hypervisor
will have a chance to synchronize the tables
the problem here is that being lazy does not
solve all the problems specifically it does
not solve the problem of having the guest
operating system removing some mappings from
the page table because in that case
since it's removing them there will not be a page fault
when it is trying to access them and
that can lead to situations in which the hypervisor
has stale shadow page tables and believes
the operating system the guest operating system
is using more memory than it is actually using
because it does not see a change in the guest
operating
system page table now here we need to differentiate
now page faults we have at this point two type
of two categories of page faults we have guest
induced page faults and hypervisor induced page faults
the guest induced page fault is a page fault
that will be intercepted by the hypervisor
for example to update the shadow page table
as
we just said but these are actually page faults
that the guest operating system needs to see
because these are the normal page faults you would have
with virtual memory so they hypervisor
then needs to re-inject the page faults into
the guest operating system so that the guest operating
system can take the actions that it is
programmed to take then
we have hypervisor induced page faults (for example
if you make the memory used by the guest operating
system to keep the page table read only)
that are only intended for the hypervisor
again to update the shadow page table for
example
but they don't need to be re-injected
into the guest operating system we say
we are observing  a VM exit whenever
a page fault results in the hypervisor gaining
control now we still have one complication
here when it comes to virtualizing memory so
forget about virtualization for a moment virtual
memory on a normal operating system as I said
lies to the processes makes them believe
that they have more memory they actually physically
have and now back to virtualization these
happens also when the hypervisor lies
to the guest operating systems pretending they
have more frames that are
actually available the problem now is what
if the hypervisor needs to reclaim some of
the frames that it assigned to a certain
operating system because another operating
system needs more frames? how can it do that?
it's similar to what you need to do when you
need to move frames from one process to the
other
the problem is that now you don't have an
operating system that sees the hardware directly
and takes decisions you have a hypervisor and
the hypervisor needs to be waken up by
the guest operating system the problem
is that the hypervisor needs frames but the
guest operating system does not need to release
frames
so how can we make the hypervisor tell the
operating system: look I need frames because
some of them need to be moved to a different
guest operating system of course I cannot
take them simply away because then you can
disrupt the memory of the guest operating
system
so a trick you can play here it's called ballooning
so you can load a small module in each machine
as a pseudodevice it's not a real device
it's a pseudodevice driver that is connected
to the hypervisor
so by doing this you create a communication
channel between the hypervisor and
each guest operating system now since the
hypervisor as control of this it can inflate
based on its own needs the amount of memory
it makes the operating system the
guest operating system believes it needs for
the driver
by doing this it will assign more frames
to the operating system but it will be in
control of those frames because they belong
to this pseudodevice driver that is controlled
by the hypervisor when the hypervisor needs
frames then it can deflate
the memory needed by the driver since it inflates
the memory that the guest operating system
would react by releasing the frames and the
hypervisor can intercept these frames and
allocate them to a different guest operating
system